(ネジ)どうしてこんな無茶を…。
Why did she do such a thing?
《サクラ : ヒナタ…》
Hinata...
You love Naruto?
《あなた ナルトのこと…》
(カツユ)ナルト君は 自分で
九尾を抑え込みました。
Naruto-kun was able to suppress
the Nine-Tails on his own.
On his own?
《自分で抑えた!?》
He is about to confront
the last Pain.
今は 最後の ペインとの決着を
つけるところです。
Lee.
(ガイ)リー。
俺たちは
ナルトの増援に向かうぞ。
We are going to assist Naruto!
(リー)はい！
(カツユ)それは… やめてください。
Right!
Please don't.
かえって ナルト君の邪魔になります。
You will only be in his way.
しかし 里をこんなにしたやつを
相手に たった一人で…。
But look what they did
to this village.
He can't manage alone!
ナルト君には 考えがあるようです。
Naruto seems to have a plan.
Let us have faith in him.
ここは 彼を信じましょう。
答えを持たぬ
お前ごときが… あきらめろ！
Someone like you who
has no answer...
should just give up!
(ナルト)うっ！ うぅ…。
耐えた… だと!?
He withstood it... Impossible!
That jutsu cannot be thrown.
《あの術は 投げ飛ばせない…
５秒… この距離ならいける》
I have five seconds.
This distance will work for me.
俺が あきらめるのを…。
Give up...
あきらめろ！
...on me giving up!
Rasengan!
螺旋丸！
Nagato...
The last Pain has been crushed.
what did I really lose that day?
ano hi honto ni ushinatta monotte nan dattakke
ぐっ…。
for the life of me I can't remember
tou ni wasureteshimatta yo
うぉ～っ！
うっ うわぁ～っ！
we slowly lost sight of each other in the twilight
yuugure de futari sukoshizutsu mienakunatteitte
and yet we're stuck here unable to go home
sore nanoni bokura kaerezu ni ita
うぅっ！ うわぁ～！
weak, frail souls lost in the world
dokoka ni kowaresou na moroi kokoro
we act strong to hide their fragility
tsuyogaru kotoba de ootte kakushiteru
(長門)うっ！ ハァ ハァ…。
hide their fragility
ootte kakushiteru
(小南)長門…。
ハァ ハァ… 最後のペインが… 潰された。
so farewell, but even forced apart
sayonara aenakunattatte
our stories go on
bokura wa tsuzuki ga aru kara
even in a world without you, I run
kimi no inai sekai datte hashiru yo
to someday get past the pain
itsuka no itami mo koete
The Two Students
ペインは こいつでチャクラを受け取って
動いていた…。
Pain operated by receiving
chakra through these sticks.
抜き取っちまえば これでもう
動けねえはずだ。
Once it's taken out,
he shouldn't be able to move anymore.
((お前も俺も
目指すものは同じだ。
You and I seek the same thing.
We are trying to establish the peace
that Jiraiya-sensei so desired.
自来也先生の言っていた平和を
成そうとしている。
You and I are not different at all.
お前も俺も何も変わらない。
互いの正義のために動く。
We each act according to
our own sense of justice.
You have your own justice...
and I have mine.
お前はお前の正義のために。
(俺は俺の正義のために))
Have you come to understand
a little of what pain is?
((少しは痛みを理解できたか？
同じ痛みを知らなければ
他人を本当には理解できない。
Unless you know the same pain,
you cannot truly know another.
(そして理解をしたところで
わかり合えるわけでもない))
And even if you get to know others,
there can be no understanding.
((憎しみの連鎖が始まる。
それが歴史だと知る。
A cycle of hatred begins.
That is history as we know it.
人は決して理解し合うことの
できない生き物だと➡
So we cannot help but believe
that human beings are incapable
of understanding each other.
悟らざるをえない。
The world of the ninja
is ruled by hatred.
(忍の世界は
憎しみに支配されている))
You're going?
行くんですか？
ああ。
Yeah.
なら 今度は増援を。
いや 駄目だ。
Then this time,
use reinforcements.
No.
一人で行く。
I'm going alone!
Hinata-sama!
ヒナタ様。
(ヒナタ)みんな。
(テンテン)よかった。 心配したよ。
Everyone...
Thank goodness!
We were so worried.
Are you okay, Hinata-san?
大丈夫ですか？ ヒナタさん。
ありがとう みんな。
ありがとう サクラさん。
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you, Sakura-san.
I'm so relieved.
You overdid yourself this time.
本当によかった。
無茶するんだから。
皆さん ナルト君が
６人目のペインを倒しました。
Everyone, Naruto-kun defeated
the sixth Pain.
やっぱりナルト君ですね。
Way to go Naruto-kun!
How is Naruto? Is he hurt?
ナルトの状態は？
怪我はどうなんです？
He's exhausted, but otherwise okay.
疲れ切っていますが大丈夫です。
Thank goodness...
Naruto-kun, I'm so glad.
《よかった。 ナルト君 よかった》
で ナルトはどこにいる？
So, where is Naruto?
He's going alone to
where the real Pain is.
ペイン本体のところへ
単独で向かっています。
Why would he do
something like that?!
なんでそんな無謀なことを。
ガイ先生 俺たちも向かおう。
Guy-sensei! We must follow!
おう。
しかし ナルト君は
増援を望んではいません。
Yes!
However... Naruto does not
want assistance.
Wh-What?!
な なに!?
駄目だ。 一人でやりすぎだ。
No! Naruto's done enough on his own!
もうナルトはかなり弱ってる。
ナルトの場所まで案内してください。
He's considerably weakened.
Please lead us to Naruto!
What is it?
どうした？
ナルトです。
It's Naruto...
ナルト！
Naruto!
Guys...
おっちゃんたち。
The fact that you're here...
お前がここにいるってことは➡
Does it mean that
you've defeated the sixth Pain?
６人目のペインに勝ったってことか？
It doesn't matter who won or lost.
勝ったとか負けたとか
そんなの関係ねえよ。
何があった？
What happened?
口ではうまく言えねえ。
I can't really put it into words.
What do you mean...
you can't put it into words?
うまく言えないとは
どういうことだ？
とにかく 俺ってば これから
ペイン本体のところへ行く。
Look, I'm going to see the real Pain.
みんなは来ないでくれ。
俺一人で行きてぇ。
Please don't follow.
I want to go alone.
ナルト ペイン本体の居場所を
知ってるのか？
Naruto, you know where
the real Pain is?!
あぁ 仙人モードで見つけた。
Yeah... I found Pain's body
through Sage Mode
ペインの体から抜き取った黒い棒から
やつのチャクラを感じたんだ。
and when I pulled out the black rod,
I felt his chakra.
なるほど。
だが一人で行きたいなどと…。
I see. But you want to go alone?
いったい どうしたんだ？
What's going on?
確かめたいことがあるんだ。
I want to confirm something.
確かめる？ 何をだ？
Confirm? What is it?
ペイン本体と話がしたい。
I want to talk to the real Pain.
なっ…
何を勝手なことを言ってるんだ！
What?! You're talking nonsense!
お前がペインを倒したことには
感謝している。
We're all grateful that
you've defeated Pain.
だが 今さら話し合いで
どうこう済む問題ではないぞ。
But it's far too late to
settle things with words!
だったら
ペイン本体も その部下も 敵の里も➡
Then tell me!
If we destroy the real Pain,
and his minions,
and the village and everything else
connected to the enemy,
すべて潰しちまえば
それで丸く治まんのか？
will that "settle" things?!
話し合って どうするというんだ。
What good will talking do?
やつは
木ノ葉を壊滅させた敵だぞ！
He is our enemy who
destroyed the Leaf Village!
許せるわけがないだろ！
We cannot forgive him!
俺だって…
俺だって そうだってばよ。
I know! I know!
I feel the same way!
木ノ葉の里を➡
How can I forgive
a guy like that
みんなを ムチャクチャにしたやつなんか
許せねえよ！
who did this to our village
and its people?!
だったら！
いのいち。
- Then...
- Inoichi...
ここはナルトの言うとおり
一人で行かせてやろうじゃないか。
Let's do as Naruto says
and let him go alone.
シカク お前！
Shikaku...
ペインを止めたのはナルトだ。
It is Naruto who stopped Pain.
ナルトにはペインと話す資格がある。
He has every right to speak to Pain.
それに こいつなりの考えが
あってのことだろう。
Besides, I'm sure he has his reasons.
しかし…。
いいから 行かせてやろう。
But...
Just let him go.
ありがとな シカクのおっちゃん。
Thanks, Old-Man Shikaku.
シカク
どうしてナルトを一人で行かせた？
Why did you let Naruto
go by himself, Shikaku?
息子だよ。
息子？
It's my son...
Your son?
((どこに行っていた？
暗号部から連絡があったぞ。
Where were you?
Black Ops sent a message for you.
(シカマル)どこって
ナルトに説教してきたんだよ。
Well... I went to lecture Naruto...
落ち込んでんじゃねえって。
to stop him from acting glum.
面倒くせえのに足が動いちまった。
It was a pain,
but I couldn't help myself.
あいつは
みんなにはない何かを持ってる。
He's got something
that we don't have.
何か？
あぁ。
"Something"?
Yeah... Someday, he's going to become
a very important ninja to this village.
いつか あいつは
この里にとって大切な忍になる。
ナルトといると➡
When I'm with Naruto...
俺は あいつと
一緒に歩いていきてえ➡
he makes me want to follow him.
(そう思わされんだ))
めったに人を褒めない あいつが
そこまで言うんだ。
Shikamaru, who rarely praises people,
said that to me.
きっとナルトには何かあるんだと
俺も信じたい。
There really must be something
special about Naruto.
I want to believe so.
ここは ナルトに託してみよう。
Let's put our faith in Naruto.
(長門)小南 下がれ。
Konan, get back.
長門…。
But Nagato...
いいんだ。
It's all right.
お前が ペインの本体か？
Are you the real Pain?
平和がノコノコやってきたか…。
So peace has stumbled onto me.
俺が憎いか？ 敵を目の前にし➡
Do you hate me?
You're facing the object
of your vendetta...
復讐を成し遂げたいだろう？
Do you wish to exact revenge?
((憎しみの連鎖が始まる。
A cycle of hatred begins.
(俺は その憎しみの連鎖を
止めるために暁を立ち上げた))
I formed the Akatsuki in order
to stop this cycle of hatred.
長門を今ここで殺し
復讐をしたところで➡
Nothing in this world will change
even if you kill Pain now
and inflict your revenge.
世の中は何も変わらない。
それは お前の自己満足だ。
All it will be is self-satisfaction.
((ミナト :  この忍のシステムがあるかぎり
憎しみというバケモノは➡
This monster known
as hate will not die
while there is a system of ninja.
また新たなペインを生み出していく。
It will give birth to more Pains.
忍とは
その憎しみとの戦いなんだ。
To be a ninja is to confront hatred.
どの忍も
その憎しみと戦っている。
Each and every one of us
battles hatred.
自来也先生は
この憎しみを終わらせる答えを➡
Jiraiya-sensei trusted you to
find a way to end this hatred.
(お前に託したんだ))
何も答えられなかったお前に
できることはない。
If you could not find the answer,
お前の役目は
俺の創り出す平和のために➡
then there is nothing you can do,
but to do the just thing
and sacrifice yourself
犠牲になるというのが正解なのだ。
for the peace which I am
about to create.
この近距離なら➡
At this close distance,
俺のチャクラで お前の動きを
思いのまま操ることができる。
I can easily control your movements
with my chakra.
安心しろ 急所は避けてある。
Rest assured.
I've avoided hitting your vital spots.
大切な人柱力だからな。
For you are invaluable, Jinchuriki.
どうしたの？ 長門。
What's wrong, Nagato?
《こいつ わざと避けずに…》
He... purposely didn't move.
お前とは
話をするつもりで ここへ来た。
I came here...
intending to talk to you.
けど他に確かめたいこともあった。
But, I also wanted to
confirm something.
確かめたいこと… だと？
Confirm... something?
自分の気持を確かめたかった。
敵を目の前にしたら➡
I wanted to confirm my feelings.
If I stood before my enemy...
俺が どうするのか
自分でもわからなかったからだ。
what would I do?
I wasn't sure of myself.
で？
And?
やっぱ てめえは許せねえ！
I can't forgive you!
今にも殺したくて
震えが止まらねえ!!
Even now, I want to kill you so badly...
I can't stop shaking!
《そんな… この近距離で➡
What? He can resist Nagato's chakra
up close like this?!
長門のチャクラに抗うなんて…》
だ～っ！
((自来也 : こんなわしでも➡
Even I can see there's too much hate
in our Ninja World.
この忍の世に 憎しみが
はびこっているのはわかる。
その憎しみを どうにかしたいとは
思っとるんだが➡
And I've wanted to do
something about this hatred,
どうしたらいいのか
わしにも まだわからん。
yet I'm not sure what must be done.
ワハハハハ！
(お前を弟子にして よかったわい))
I'm glad I made you my student.
エロ仙人は 本当の意味で➡
Pervy Sage said he believed
that the day would come
理解しあえる時代がくるって➡
信じてるって言った。
when people can truly understand
one another.
その話をしてくれたとき 俺は➡
I wasn't paying much attention
when he told me that...
適当にしか聞いてなくって…。
俺に そのやり方の答えを
託すって言ってくれたのが➡
Even when he said he'd entrust me
with finding the answer.
ただ 弟子として
認められたみたいで➡
I got excited, taking it as a sign
嬉しかっただけだった。
that he acknowledged me
as his student.
今になって やっと
エロ仙人の言ってた意味がわかる。
Thinking back...
I finally understand what
Pervy Sage meant.
そんな
簡単なもんじゃねえんだって。
That it's not so simple.
だが 俺を許せないことに
変わりはないはずだ。
Still, it doesn't change the fact
that you can't forgive me.
きれいごとで許せるほど
人の愛情は安くはない。
Words of forgiveness come easy.
Love does not.
あぁ 確かに
そのとおりだってばよ。
Yeah... You're right about that.
自来也先生の言っていたことは
時代遅れの理想主義だ。
Jiraiya-sensei's words reflect
an idealism from an era long past.
現実は違いすぎる。
It is far removed from reality.
お前は俺を倒し
忍の世界を平和にしてやると➡
Didn't you say you would kill me
and bring peace to the Ninja World?
言っていたはずだが…。
たとえ それが建て前で➡
Even if you seek vengeance
for your own satisfaction,
おのれの自己満足のための
復讐だとしても➡
それが お前の正義なら
それでいい。
if that is your idea of justice,
so be it.
お前は神じゃない。
You're not a god.
この現実を目の当たりにし
お前は本当に➡
After witnessing this harsh reality,
do you really still believe
Jiraiya-sensei's silly ramblings?
自来也先生の戯れごとを
信じることができるのか？
お前が エロ仙人の弟子だと
わかったとき どうしても➡
When I found out you were
Pervy Sage's student,
I wanted to ask you one thing.
聞いておきたいことができた。
なんだ？
What is it?
エロ仙人の弟子だった お前たちが➡
How could the Pervy Sage's students
turn out the way you did?
どうして こうなっちまったのか。
お前たちは
今までの暁のやつらみてえに➡
I understand that you're not
like the Akatsuki members
ただ 殺戮を楽しむ
やつらじゃねえのは わかった。
who kill out of sheer enjoyment.
けど 俺は
お前たちのことを何も知らねえ。
But I don't know a thing
about you guys.
だから 話を聞いて
それから答えを出したい。
That's why...
I want to hear your stories,
then come up with an answer.
いいだろう。
Very well...
俺たちの痛みを 教えてやる。
We will tell you about our pain.
when the fireworks suddenly explode in the air
fui ni agatta hanabi wo futari de miageta toki
I couldn't keep my eyes off from your face
muchuu de miteru kimi no kao wo
I gazed at you quietly
sotto nusumimita no
it'd be so much easier if I was able to hate you
kimi no koto kirai ni naretara ii noni
because I always remember you in situations like this
kyou mitai na hi ni wa kitto
I can't help but think about the times we spent together
mata omoidashiteshimau yo
I'm ready to forget you
mou wasureyou kimi no koto zenbu
it just tears at my heart too much
konna ni mo kanashikute
I wonder why did we meet each other
doushite deatteshimattan darou
when I close my eyes
me wo tojireba
It's like you are here
ima mo kimi ga soko ni iru you de
Next Episode
(ウェンディ)ルーシィさん
ありがとうございます！
Did you hear, Sakura?
(ルーシィ)どういたしまして。
The next Naruto Shippuden is about an untold tale
キャンサーってわけにはいかないけど
私だって なかなかのものでしょ。
that takes place back when we were kids!
Team 7 goes on a great adventure
はい とっても上手です！
in search of the Fourth Hokage's legacy.
それに 外でこうしていると
気持いいですね！
You definitely have to see this one!
Check out all our action!
And Sasuke-kun's heroics!
Don't miss out on it!
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "Big Adventure! The Quest for the Fourth Hokage's Legacy - Part 1"
Big Adventure! The Quest for the Fourth Hokage's Legacy - Part 1
Now go, young challengers!
Master, I heard you used to
change your age and appearance
as you travelled around.
As a young kid...
as a lovesick adolescent,
and such.
Wow...
I'm interested to know what you
looked like in your youth, Tsunade-sama.
Oh, me too!
Hmm... Very well then!
Well? Pretty charming,
don't you think?
Huh?
Wh-What's with you two?!
I-Is there something
you want to say?
Wh-Wh-What?
- That...
- Turns into that?!
Tsunade-sama! What was your diet
like during adolescence?
And any other secrets you have!
- Tell us already!
Cut it out!